Guide to the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850, 1888-2000s and undated, bulk 1920-2008 RL.00936
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Company Offices, 1850, 1898-2008 and undated; 1920-2000; 86 boxes plus oversize containers
  - Office of the President, 1903-2002 and undated; 1950s-1990s
    - Asa T. Spaulding, 1932-1969 and undated
      - NCM publications, 1947, 1966 (Box 35)
      - N.L. Gregg retirement, 1966 (Box 35)
      - Northern Frontier Planning Committee - Appreciation Production to President Asa T. Spaulding, 1959 (Box 35)
      - Partners in Business by A.T. Spaulding, 1940 (Box 35)
      - Pay stabilization, 1951 and undated (Box 35)
      - Progress report, 1963 (Box 35)
      - Releases and speeches, 1943, 1956, 1961-1963, 1968-1969 (Box 35)
      - Report to the Policyholders, 1961-1968, 3 folders (Box 35)
      - Special Reports on Major Business Problems from Business Week, 1965 (Box 35)
      - Speeches, 1932, 1938, 1956, 1964-1967, 2 folders (Box 35)
      - The Presidents' Council of the American Institute of Management, 1965 (Box 35)
      - Youth opportunity campaign, 1965 (Box 35)
    - Joseph W. Goodloe, 1965-1972
      Goodloe served as President from 1968-1972. Contains some material from his time as Corporate Secretary. There are very few materials present within the collection from Goodloe's tenure at NCM.
      - Philadelphia office 30th anniversary, 1968 (Box 32)
      - Dedication Committee for new home office - Mutual Plaza, 1965-1966, 2 folders (Box 32)
      - Letter concerning employment contracts for former Unity Mutual Life Insurance Company officials, 1971 (Box 35)
      - Report to policyholders, 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 35)
    - William J. Kennedy, III, 1934-1990 and undated; 1960s-1990; 7 boxes
      Kennedy, III, son of William Kennedy Jr., served as President of NC Mutual from 1972-1990. Material relates to general company business, external and internal correspondence, mergers with and reinsurance of other insurance companies, and information pertaining to other organizations with which NC Mutual was affiliated (the contents are categorized as: company business/personnel, correspondence, other insurance companies, and other organizations).
      [Some personnel records were removed to Personnel Subseries and are closed for 75 years from date of creation of most recent record or 2074.]
      - Company Business/Personnel
        Contains material relating to both financial and non-financial aspects of the company business, including but not limited to matters relating to personnel. Material is organized alphabetically by the size of the material. There is also one personal letter from his parents, 1958.
        - Accountants' Opinion report, 1981 Dec. 31 (Box 36)
        - Asa T. Spaulding Insurance Hall of Fame, 1984-1985 (Box 36)
        - Banquet tributes, 1978 and undated (Box 36)
        - Blank retirement Certificate of Service, undated (Box 36)
        - Blue Cross Blue Shield stock purchase, 1986 Nov.-1987 Jan. (Box 36)
        - Board of Directors fees and committees of the Board, 1985 Mar. (Box 36)
        - Board items, 1973-1984, 1989 and undated (Box 36)
        - Construction offers, 1988 (Box 36)
        - Cost Committee: Life Office Management Association, 1954-1963, 3 folders (Box 36)
        - Employee and committee info for NCM Board of Directors, 1970, 1973, 1984-1987 (Box 36)
        - Executive compensation proposals and plans, 1982-1990, 14 folders (Box 181)
          Comprises planning documents addressing NCM executive compensation plans, with proposals submitted by E.F. Hutton, Hays Associates consultants, and Northwestern Mutual Life. Folders also house memos, notes and correspondence.
        - Executive compensation proposals and plans, 1982-1990, 12 folders (Box 182)
        - Executive compensation proposals and plans, 1982-1990, 2 folders in half-size box (Box 183)
        - Harvard Business Review, 1973 (Box 36)
        - Historic documents: Centennial of Durham's Stanford-Warren library, 1990; obituaries for William Kennedy Jr., 1985, and N. H. Beale, 1990 (Box 36)
        - Historical Experience of the Reinsured Group Business, 1976 (Box 36)
        - Historical Sketch by W.J. Kennedy, Jr., three versions circa 1934, 1949, 1957 (Box 36)
          This sketch was written by William Kennedy III's father, William Kennedy Jr., but was found among the son's papers. Other drafts and research materials are found in the William Kennedy Jr. Subseries.
        - Introduction to Life/70, Student Guide, circa 1978, 2 folders (Box 36)
        - Introduction to Life/70, Textbook, circa 1978 (Box 37)
        - Martin Luther King Jr. memorial program, 1985 (Box 37)
        - Merrick-Moore scholarship advertising, press releases, clippings, 1935-1936 (Box 37)
          [The contents of this folder are fragile and in need of preservation. Please contact Research Services to use this material, as material should be photocopied before handling.]
        - Md. Insurance Division hearing in petition for approval of contract and reinsurance of Mutual Benefit Society of Baltimore, 1977 (Box 37)
        - Miscellaneous company business, circa 1970s (Box 37)
        - New South Life Insurance Company financial statements and information, 1973-1975 (Box 37)
        - North American Insurance Company contracts, 1980 (Box 37)
        - NCM book review (Box 37)
        - NCM building, Vierendeel trusses, 1977-1980 (Box 37)
        - NCM employee evaluation plan, 1961-1962 (Box 37)
        - NCM Employment handbook, guidelines, and company information, undated (Box 37)
        - NCM Group Reinsurance Program report, 1982 July 28 (Box 37)
        - NCM long range planning manual - 1st draft, 1973 (Box 37)
        - NCM Moving to...Mutual Plaza, 1965 (Box 37)
        - Photos - WJK III, Heritage room, undated (Box 37)
        - Report on examination of NCM, 1962, 1968, 1983, 1986, 4 folders (Box 37)
        - Time capsule placement ceremony, 1963 Oct. 20 (Box 37)
        - Claim settlement practices in Virginia, 1978 (Box 38)
        - Documents relating to the reinsurance of North American Insurance Company, 1974-1980 (Box 38)
        - Insurance Certificates of Authority, 1977 (Box 38)
        - Miscellaneous company business, 1977 and undated (Box 38)
        - Notes, 1984-1986 (Box 38)
        - Releases, agreements, and contracts for reinsurance, 1970-1975 (Box 38)
        - Various personal insurance policies and invoices for W.J. Kennedy, III, 1946, 1953-1965, 3 folders (Box 38)
        - Personal letter to Kennedy from mother and father, William Kennedy Jr., on vacation trip to New Mexico, 1958 Sept. 24 (Box 38)
        - Various NCM committee agendas and plans, 1988-1989 (Box 38)
      - Correspondence
        Materials include chronologically-ordered internal and external correspondence with the Office of the President under William J. Kennedy, III. Also includes various NCM memoranda.
        - Correspondence-External, 1973-1974, 1982-1983, 1988-1990, 2 folders (Box 39)
        - Internal correspondence and memos, 1972-1974, 1978-1982 (Box 39)
        - Essence magazine correspondence for possible investment, 1973 (Box 39)
        - Goodloe policy inquiry and correspondence, 1947-1948, 1988 (Box 39)
        - Insurance Holding Company Act, Linville Roach, 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 39)
        - National Employers Security Trust, 1976 (Box 39)
        - Virginia Mutual, 1975 (Box 39)
      - Other Insurance Companies
        Contains material relating to annual/financial statements, contracts, and correspondence with other insurance companies that were associated with NC Mutual in terms of mergers and reinsurance.
        - Annual Statement of the Southern Life Insurance Company, 1983 (Box 38)
        - All American Assurance Company annual statements and minutes, 1974-1976, 2 folders (Box 38)
        - American Citizens Life Insurance Corporation information and annual statement, 1978-1979, 2 folders (Box 38)
        - Bradford's Industrial Insurance Co. annual statement and examination, 1977-1981 (Box 40)
        - Chicago Metropolitan Mutual Assurance Company:
          - Annual statements, examinations, business records, 1965-1975, 1978, 4 folders (Box 40)
          - Merger agreement, circa 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 40)
          - Policy samples, undated (Box 40)
        - Mammoth Insurance Company merger, 1985 (Box 40)
        - Mutual Benefit Society of Baltimore City contract information, merger, and historical sketch, 1977-1978, 2 folders (Box 40)
        - NC Mutual budget statements and merger information, 1978, 2 folders (Box 40)
        - New South Life Insurance Company records, 1978 (Box 40)
        - North Carolina Insurance Code and purchasing/selling of other insurance companies, 1978 (Box 40)
        - Other insurance companies annual statements, 1975-1986 (Box 40)
        - Provident Home Industrial Insurance Company merger and miscellaneous info, 1974-1975, 1981, 2 folders (Box 41)
        - Pyramid Life Insurance, 1969-1970, 1975 (Box 41)
        - Southern Aid Life Insurance annual statement, 1986 (Box 41)
        - Southern Life Insurance Company, 1977 (Box 41)
        - Union Protective Life Insurance Company business records, 1973-1975 (Box 41)
        - United Mutual Insurance Company of NY annual statement and information, 1985-1987, 3 folders (Box 41)
        - Universal Life Insurance Company of Memphis annual statement, 1979 (Box 41)
        - Various merged companies' financial information, 1975-1977 (Box 41)
        - Virginia Mutual Benefit Life Insurance Company:
          - Annual statement, 1984 (Box 41)
          - Acquisition, 1985-1988, 2 folders (Box 41)
          - Miscellaneous files, 1988 (Box 41)
        - Winston Mutual Life Insurance Company annual statements, 1973, 1975, 1983 (Box 41)
      - Other Organizations
        Includes material relating to business meetings, memoranda, and other miscellaneous information concerning organizations outside of North Carolina Mutual with which William J. Kennedy, III and NCM were affiliated. Material is organized alphabetically.
        - American Capital Life Insurance Company, 1986-1988 (Box 42)
        - American Citizens Life Insurance portfolio summary, 1979 (Box 42)
        - Chicago Metropolitan: Employee information, 1969, 1972 (Box 42)
        - Chicago Metropolitan: Labor union agreement, 1970 (Box 42)
        - Chicago Metropolitan: Merger information, contracts, 1974 (Box 42)
        - Chicago Metropolitan: Significant financials, reports, 1973 (Box 42)
        - Citizens Security Life Insurance Co. and American Capital Life Insurance Co., co-insurance agreement, 1980 (Box 42)
        - Deloitte, Haskins, and Sells, 1980 Dec. 12 (Box 42)
        - NC Association of Life Insurance Companies, 1985-1990 and undated, 5 folders (Box 42)
        - Opportunities Industrialization Centers, 1986-1989, 2 folders (Box 42)
        - Virginia Mutual Life Insurance Co., 1988 (Box 42)
        - Winston Mutual Life Insurance Co. merger information and finances, 1974, 1977, 1984 (Box 42)
    - Bert Collins, 1943-2002 and undated; 1970s-1994; 23 boxes
      Collins served as the President of NC Mutual from 1990-2003. Prior to his role as president, Collins served as an Executive Vice President for the company. Includes documents dating from when he first joined the company in the 1970s through until near the end of his tenure as president, with the majority of the material dating from 1985-1994. The contents are organized into four categories: budget/finance, company business/personnel, correspondence, and other organizations. Some personnel records were removed to Personnel Subseries. Arranged in rough alphabetical order or in original order as received. There are many records pertaining to Collins's affiliation with North Carolina Central University.
      - Budget/Finance
        Contains material relating to financial aspects of NCM company business. Examples include company audits, budgets, financial reports, bills for service and pension account reports. Organized alphabetically by folder title.
        - Budgets (proposed), 1988, 1990 (Box 43)
        - Business plans and budgets, Insurance OPS, 1990 (Box 43)
        - Check requisitions, bills for service, receipts ledger entries, 1990-1994, 4 folders (Box 43)
        - Claims, 1988-1990 (Box 43)
        - Comparative Statement of Budget and Actual Income and Disbursements for 1991 Sept. 30 (Box 43)
        - Corporate business plan, 1988 Nov. 16 (Box 43)
        - Employee Pension Account reports, 1987 (Box 43)
        - First Capital Life payments, 1986-1989 (Box 43)
        - First Capital Life and E.F. Hutton business records (financial), 1986-1991 (Box 43)
        - Internal audit, budget, reports, clearing checks, general finance, 1986-1992, 5 folders (Box 43)
        - Internal audit, budget, reports, clearing checks, 1992-1994, 2 folders (Box 44)
        - Mechanic and Farmer's Bank statement, 1971-1972 (Box 44)
        - Ostine Swan - Review Audit Plan, 1995 (Box 44)
        - PW Trust Company, 1994 (Box 44)
        - Custom Transaction Listings, 1990 July-Nov., 1992 Aug. 13, 2 folders (Box 66)
        - Group Reinsurance Contingency Reserves, 1990 (Box 66)
        - Premium income by week, 1990 (Box 66)
        - Securities Committee minutes, 1987-1990 (Box 66)
      - Company business/Personnel
        Contains material relating to non-financial aspects of the company business, including but not limited to matters relating to personnel. Documents are organized alphabetically. Non-NCM printed material is located in the "N" section and includes material such as various business articles, the Durham Rotary Bulletin, and photocopies of newspaper clippings. Similar material can be found in the Printed Material Series.
        [Confidential material has been removed to Personnel Subseries and is closed for 75 years from date of creation of most recent record or 2074.]
        - 20th anniversary of Mutual Plaza, 1968-1988 (Box 45)
        - Ad hoc committee to study use of Home Office facilities, 1976 (Box 45)
        - A.J. Rivers retirement, 1990 (Box 45)
        - Asa T. Spaulding Insurance Hall of Fame candidacy information, 1943-1953, 1961-1971, 1990-1991 (Box 45)
        - Bachrach Studio - Presidential photo, 1991 (Box 45)
        - Claims, 1988-1990 (Box 45)
        - Collins promotion congrats and clippings, 1987 (Box 45)
        - Collins speeches and remarks, 1991 (Box 45)
        - Compensation Task Force, 1987 (Box 45)
        - Complaints, 1988-1992 (Box 45)
        - Conflict of Interest forms, 1994 (Box 45)
        - Control Environment questionnaire, undated (Box 45)
        - Copies of memos to Board of Directors, 1980-1983 (Box 45)
        - Data Processing Project 4, 1987 Mar. (Box 45)
        - Data Processing Task Force, 1989 May-July (Box 45)
        - Directions and Goals: Field Operations, 1984 (Box 45)
        - Disaster Plans - letters, 1973 (Box 45)
        - District mergers, 1988 (Box 45)
        - Dr. Charles Watts, 1987 (Box 45)
        - Duties of the System Coordinator, undated (Box 45)
        - Electronic Data Systems, 1989-1990 (Box 45)
        - Employee and Management evaluation, analysis, and improvement, 1985, 9 of 13 folders (Box 45)
        - Employee and Management evaluation, analysis, and improvement, 1985, 4 of 13 folders (Box 46)
        - Employee personal computers, 1985-1987, undated (Box 46)
        - Employee Performance Reports material, undated (Box 46)
        - Environmental Task Force, 1989 May-July (Box 46)
        - Field Committee, 1986-1987, 2 folders (Box 46)
        - Field Accounting System, 1982-1990, 5 folders (Box 46)
        - Founders' Day, 1987 (Box 46)
        - Furniture and fixtures, 1984-1989, undated (Box 46)
        - Goodloe policy, Parrish policy, 1990 (Box 46)
        - Hay Management Consultants report and recommendations for Incentive Program, 1985 Nov. (Box 46)
        - Historical documents, 1989 (Box 47)
        - Home Office appointments, 1990-1993 (Box 47)
        - John Tyler Caldwell Award for Humanities Program (Honoree: John Hope Franklin), 1991 (Box 47)
        - Management Development program, 1985-1986 (Box 47)
        - Memorex maintenance agreement, 1985 (Box 47)
        - Merger of Mutual Community Savings Bank with Greensboro National Bank, 1994 (Box 47)
        - Miscellaneous company business, 1989-1994, 5 folders (Box 47)
        - NCM business plans for 1989-1992, 1989 (Box 47)
        - NCM Life Communications sale of Williamsburg, Va. radio stations, 1985 (Box 47)
        - NC Mutual Re-engineering project, 1994 (Box 47)
        - Non-NCM printed material: Performance Appraisals that Measure Up, 1985 (Box 47)
        - Non-NCM printed material: United Nations Biography: Joseph Nanven Garba (Nigeria), circa 1989 (Box 47)
        - Non-NCM printed material, 1989-1994, 5 folders (Box 47)
        - Office maps, 1986 and undated (Box 48)
        - Orphan photo, undated (Box 48)
        - Personnel:
          [All of these files have been removed to the Personnel Subseries and are closed for 75 years from date of creation of most recent record or 2074.]
          - Pension Fund Manager, 1990 (Box 48)
          - Pension Investment, 1986-1988 (Box 48)
          - Pensions and Retirement, 1986 (Box 48)
          - Pension Retirement Plan Committee - appointments and resignations, 1991 (Box 48)
          - 12th floor personnel, 1988 (Box 48)
          - Absenteeism and Tardiness policy, 1986 (Box 48)
          - Changes in assignment and promotion, 1979-1989 and undated (Box 48)
          - Craig Page - RDU Airport, 1990 (Box 48)
          - Letters of recommendation, 1974-1990 and undated (Box 48)
          - Personnel matters, 1988-1994, 5 folders (Box 48)
          - Org charts and personnel listings, 1990 and undated (Box 48)
          - Reference letters, 1991 Sept.-Oct. (Box 48)
          - Salary policy and examination, 1986 (Box 48)
          - Sexual Harassment policy, undated (Box 48)
          - Suggestion plan, 1985-1990 and undated (Box 48)
        - Planning, 1989 (Box 48)
        - Policy approval material, 1983-1989 and undated (Box 48)
        - Press release, 1988 (Box 48)
        - Program to conserve NAIC business, 1980 (Box 48)
        - Retirement and Welfare Plan summary annual reports, 1988-1989 (Box 48)
        - Revoked CPA license, 1983 (Box 48)
        - Planning documents and reports: staffing plans, Underwriting and Actuarial Depts., Human Resources, 1980s-1990s (Box 48-A)
        - Retirement plans: Great West Life payments, 1989-1991, Capital Life documents, executive compensation, 1989 (Box 48-A)
        - Profitability Task Force: (Box 49)
          - NC Mutual annual statement, 1982 (Box 49)
          - Minutes and agenda, 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 49)
        - Profitability Task Force, Studies:
          - Agency, 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 49)
          - Controller and misc., 1983 (Box 49)
          - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 49)
          - Direct group, 1983 (Box 49)
          - Executive Committee recommendations, 1983 (Box 49)
          - Financial data, 1983 (Box 49)
          - Hospitalization - Employee benefits, 1983 (Box 49)
          - Re-insurance and EDP, 1983 (Box 49)
        - Speeches: (Box 50)
          - Boy Scout Troop 55, 1992 (Box 50)
          - District offices, 1975, 1980-1990, and undated, 2 folders (Box 50)
          - Dr. Donna Benson, Vita - Introduction, 1992 (Box 50)
          - Durham Business and Professional Chain banquet - Kenneth Chenault, 1991 (Box 50)
          - Durham Business and Professional Chain banquet - Tony Brown, 1992 (Box 50)
          - Speech file, 1990-1991 and undated (Box 50)
          - Goldsboro district home office visit, 1992 June 25 (Box 50)
          - Good Idea speech material, undated (Box 50)
          - Greetings, 1991 (Box 50)
          - Impact of violence on the business community, undated (Box 50)
          - Introduction for Dr. Anderson, Black Labor, White Wealth, 1994 (Box 50)
          - Health Care, 1992 Nov. 18 (Box 50)
          - Life/70 training, 1992 June 19 (Box 50)
          - Mel Watt introduction, 1993 Aug. 1 (Box 50)
          - Miscellaneous speech material, 1991-1998 and undated (Box 50)
          - Receptions, 1990-1991 (Box 50)
        - Sayre and Sayre, 1989 (Box 51)
        - Southwood Landscaping contract, 1982 (Box 51)
        - Suggestion Committee, Good Idea campaign, 1991 (Box 51)
        - Survey results, 1988 (Box 51)
        - Survey of mutual life insurance companies, 1986 (Box 51)
        - Team Leader Task Force, 1988, 14 folders (Box 51)
        - Telecommunications, 1983-1986 (Box 51)
        - Today's mail, 1993 Feb. 9 (Box 51)
        - Board meeting, 1985, 3 folders (Box 66)
        - Employee Agreements, 1974-1988 and undated (Box 66)
        - Employee Group Health Plan, 1984-1988 (Box 66)
        - Equipment lease file, et al., 1985-1986 (Box 66)
        - Miscellaneous documents, 1990 and undated (Box 66)
        - Collins, Bar exam, 1970 (Box 66)
        - Rolling Hills - Offer to purchase and contract, 1990 (Box 66)
        - Salary study, 1970, 1977, 1984 (Box 66)
        - Whetstone Editorial Board, 1988 (Box 66)
      - Correspondence
        Materials include chronologically-ordered internal and external correspondence with the Office of the President and the Office of the Executive Vice President under Bert Collins. Also includes North Carolina Mutual committees' meeting minutes and information, and NCM memoranda.
        - Correspondence-External: (Box 52)
          - 1978 June, 1984 Feb., 1987-1990, 4 folders (Box 52)
          - Collins promotion congratulations, thank you's and announcement addresses, 1990 (Box 52)
          - 1991-1994, 5 folders (Box 52)
          - General solicitations, 1989-1994, 10 folders (Box 53)
        - Internal memoranda and meetings: (Box 54)
          - 1984-1988 (Box 54)
          - NCM Board of Directors meeting, 1989 May 24, 2 folders (Box 54)
          - NCM Board of Directors meeting, 1989 July 26, 2 folders (Box 54)
          - 1989-1994, 4 folders (Box 54)
        - Correspondence-Internal: (Box 55)
          - 1989-1991 and undated, 2 folders (Box 55)
          - Letters to District Managers, 1991 Oct. (Box 55)
          - 1992-1994 (Box 55)
        - Other correspondence:
          - Attorney Charles McClain, 1994 (Box 55)
          - Black Directory information and business plan, 1990-1992 (Box 55)
          - Correspondence with Black Enterprise, 1993 Mar.-Apr. (Box 55)
          - Charles Ray - proposal, 1994 (Box 55)
          - C.C. Spaulding papers - Duke Library, 1999-2000 (Box 55)
          - Department of Insurance - various states, 1990-1994 (Box 55)
          - Dollars and Sense 1993 Jan. issue, solicitation and correspondence (Box 55)
          - Draft letter to A.M. Best Co. from Bert Collins, 2002 (Box 55)
          - EEOC Notice of Charge of Discrimination, 1989 (Box 55)
          - Government departments and agencies, 1989-1994 (Box 55)
          - Motivational sales letters, 1993 (Box 55)
          - Shaw University campaign, 1992 (Box 55)
          - The Continuum Co. correspondence, 1982-1989 (Box 55)
          - Tillinghast correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 55)
          - Additional correspondence and memoranda, 1990-1991 (Box 66)
      - Other Organizations
        Contains files with business meeting notes, memoranda, retreat information, and other papers concerning organizations outside of NCM with which Bert Collins and NCM were affiliated. Connections to these organizations range from philanthropical donations to holding a seat on a Board of Executives. Material is organized alphabetically.
        - General Files
          - Air Atlanta, 1986-1987 (Box 56)